[Music]
do
hello good evening good day and welcome
to the latest episode of the ask a
widget show i hope you are all doing
very well
today we discuss science
which is everyone's favorite subject as
we know uh so let's see who all is there
with us today
you can see praful crazy brain durga and
dr nish alpha rishikesh
nikhil vinith prabhal john
and lots of other people let's see who
all who else is there
pratik nikhil ayush
shivaji itape
anish shri harsha lineshwar descendant
of rigvedic clans
sahil verma
neel and lots of other people shashank
shurweer
edits someone kumudini manojit roger
fighter jason
and so on good evening good day all of
you
so
shall we get into the questions as we
always do without further ado let's get
right into the questions
samira joshi says why don't we feel the
earth's rotation um why don't we feel it
so the earth
the earth rotates goes round and round
right
so why don't we feel that and the
rotation speed is reasonably fast uh
let's take a look at the screen shall we
what does the earth look like
the earth is a planet
um google maps various maps here is maps
so it's a it's reasonably round and it
rotates it rotates from east to west
i believe that's the rotation direction
or whatever it is i mean the sun rises
in the east that's what we know and the
earth's rotation is reasonably fast i
mean 500 kilometers per per hour per
second something like that whatever it
is you can look it up it's a fast
rotation so the question is why don't we
feel it why aren't we thrown away when
the earth because of the earth rotation
why are we just here where we are and we
feel nothing think about it this way
let's say you're sitting in a car the
car is traveling at let's say 50
kilometers an hour on your road
yes
do you feel something happening
you feel some some movement from time to
time which is when the car accelerates
or decelerates or changes direction but
if it is just going straight
without changing its speed or velocity
you feel nothing you can just sit
comfortably in there and nothing happens
let's imagine you're sitting in a plane
in an aircraft so the aircraft it you
get inside you say you take your seat
and all all the formalities are done
then the aircraft goes towards the
runway yeah
then it lines up with the runway and
then it the pilot turns on throttles the
engines
and the engines go full blast and that's
when you are pushed back
against your chair right when the plane
accelerates so once again it's only when
you're pushed back when the plane
accelerates and changes speed that you
feel the movement but once you're in the
air once everything settles down you
feel nothing you can walk around and do
whatever you want you can have food yes
so
the same thing happens on the earth when
you're sitting on the planet the planet
is moving at the same speed the speed
isn't changing there is no acceleration
or deceleration that's why you feel
nothing
right you're essentially in a
quasi-inertial frame of reference that's
that's that's how it feels like from
your perspective it's not exactly an
inertial frame of preference but
yeah so
so as long as there is no no
acceleration or deceleration you're
gonna feel nothing because you are
attached to the planet your feet your
chair whatever your bed yeah
and you are part of it essentially and
you feel nothing because it's actually
it's going on at the same speed
the the the
the rotation isn't slowing down or
speeding up if for whatever reason the
rotation were to suddenly speed up yeah
that's when you will feel it that's when
it will be thrown up thrown in
some direction
or for some reason if the rotation were
to suddenly slow down you would again
feel the same kind of thing and you'll
be thrown in the opposite direction
but as long as the rotation is the same
the same speed you feel nothing because
of how you feel in a car when the car is
going at the same speed in a straight
line you feel nothing when you're
sitting in a plane the plane is flying
at the same speed
you feel nothing right and when the
plane is taking off or or landing or
when there is bad weather the the seat
belt sign comes on so that's what tells
you that yeah right now there's going to
be some acceleration or deceleration or
movement from side to side and we need
to be in the chair otherwise we will be
thrown out we will be we will face some
kind of problem
uh staying where we are so that's why we
need to sit down and put on the seatbelt
and that's how it goes so that in brief
is why we do not feel the rotation of
the earth
okay let's take another question the
next one
swapnil mishra says
uh two questions
firstly which aspects of photosynthesis
are still not well understood by science
and secondly since solar panels take up
so much land space is it possible to
optimize plants directly or inertly to
harness solar energy through artificial
photosynthesis by converting sunlight
plus carbon dioxide plus water into
clean clean fuel okay
so uh
photosynthesis which aspects of
photosynthesis are not well understood
by science so first let's talk about
what we do understand about
photosynthesis photosynthesis is the
the it's the it's the process the
reaction by which plants
convert sunlight and water
and carbon dioxide into a different a
different form of energy which is
essentially glucose and carbohydrates
and they give off
oxygen as as a byproduct right so how
does this happen
plants have leaves we know them right we
know we see leaves everywhere yep
these leaves they uh
in the cells of these leaves
there are organelles so like in the
human body there are organs within a
cell within the cells in our bodies and
in the cells of plants you have
organelles which are different
components that carry out various
functions so one of these organelles
inside a cell
inside
a plant cell a leaf cell is called a
chloroplast
chloroplast now this chloroplast
organelle contains a pigment claw called
chlorophyll
now what does this chlorophyll do it's
it's a pigment it absorbs energy from
the light waves which is the rays of the
sun the photons that come from the sun
if you look at the sun's light it is
white light it looks yellowish but it's
actually white light it's a combination
of all the different colors of the
visible spectrum and much more
so it's white light so the chlorophyll
absorbs not all of this light but some
of this light it absorbs the light
photons
in the blue part of the spectrum
and the red part of the spectrum and it
reflects photons in the green part of
the spectrum which is why plants and
their leaves appear green
okay so the chlorophyll absorbs this
sunlight the energy from these
light waves
and this energy
is converted into chemical energy in the
forms of a couple of molecules atp it is
only eddy no adinosine triphosphate and
something called nadph which you can
look up i don't remember the exact uh
full form but these are two molecules
that uh store energy essentially they
are related to the energy and we also
have atp etc in our in our bodies
so chlorophyll
by some process absorbs these photons
that come in from the sunlight in
certain color ranges yeah and then there
is a process that takes place which
converts so not only the the sunlight is
required you also need carbon dioxide so
carbon dioxide is present in some
quantities in the atmosphere yes so the
carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and
water from the soil
so the plants they they extract water
out of the soil through the roots they
then
the process of photosynthesis also needs
carbon dioxide and sunlight
certain
certain uh frequencies or wavelength of
sunlight so then what happens is there
is a process that takes place which is
not very well understood which converts
oxygen
in water
sorry it converts it takes water plus
carbon dioxide plus energy from the
sunlight and it that gives you glucose
so it is what is the chemical reaction
like it is six
it is six
h2o
plus six co2 which gives you one
molecule
of uh glucose plus some extra oxygen is
given out yeah that's typically how it
is you can i'm sure it's all available
online you can look it up so that's how
it works
uh
now how does this happen it is a
question so
the process of photosynthesis is is
something that happens with the help of
certain proteins
there are certain proteins that act like
antennas they receive the photons they
they take the photons and then this
then the energy is passed into a
molecular machine
essentially within
the within the plant's
insides yeah within the cell
and this molecular machine
operates at the molecular and atomic
level and we don't quite know how this
works and that's where the conversion of
all of this happens the chemical
reaction happens now we can take
photographs through through via
microscopes electron microscopes or
whatever but
it only shows you a photograph a
snapshot of a dynamic process now inside
inside the plant you have living
material right these proteins are
synthesized they degrade the new protein
is synthesized this entire molecular
machinery is
something that is dynamic
it lasts for a while then it degrades
and then it is replaced by something new
and this process is also very dynamic it
happens on in an ongoing fashion and
even if we take photographs or we take
uh scanning tunneling my electron
microscope images we only see a snapshot
of something that is a long process so
that's why we don't quite understand how
it happens and of course this happens at
the at the
molecular and atomic level which is the
realm of quantum mechanics so once again
we don't quite know how this happens and
that's that's the that's the part where
we don't quite understand right because
we don't have the means of peering deep
inside and seeing things happen
dynamically in real time at the atomic
and molecular level so that's where we
don't quite know how it happens now
photosynthesis itself is not a very
efficient uh process
of all the energy that's incident upon
upon a plant leaf i think about about
between three and eleven percent is used
is actually utilized by the process of
photosynthesis more than ninety percent
of the essentially ninety percent or
more of the energy that's incident on
the leaf is uh not utilized in
photosynthesis
uh so it's not a very efficient process
and yet it's way more efficient than our
solar panels and all that
so there is a
there's research ongoing
into how to uh how to do artificial
photosynthesis because that would be
great because you know yeah so uh now
the second question is about solar
panels they take up too much space is it
possible to just optimize plants to
harness solar energy through artificial
photosynthesis
this matter well to do that we would
have to understand how the process works
thoroughly you need to understand how
the process works and you need to be
able to replicate that in in a
repeatable manner and we are not yet
quite quite there yet because we don't
understand how it works at the uh
molecular and atomic level we don't even
understand the molecular the the
molecular reactor essentially which
which
uh which makes the process happen so
yeah we are not there if we can
do i mean
create a machinery molecular machinery
that can do artificial photosynthesis
that would be a great leap forward then
you could have artificial plants or or
or bio-engineered plants or whatever it
is that could help us
um
in some way harness solar energy more
efficiently
than than the
then how solar panels do it
so yeah we are there is research that's
ongoing in various parts of the world
about how to about possibly having a
breakthrough and achieving the
artificial photosynthesis but we are not
quite there yet we are still quite a way
far from there and it's strange because
photosynthesis is is what gave birth to
life essentially in on our planet uh if
you look at the history of the earth
the
first unambiguous evidence that we have
of life it dates back to about 3.77
billion years before today right the
planet is about four and a half billion
years old so around three point seven
seven billion years before today you had
the first life
on the planet and most of the
original life the earliest life was
photosynthetic life you had
cyanobacteria and various other
unicellular organisms eventually they
gave rise to multicellular organisms and
all of these relied on photosynthesis
and photosynthesis essentially takes the
sunlight it
uses water and carbon dioxide to produce
uh
glucose and various carbohydrates
starches and all that and that's what
plants that's what sustains plants and
it is herbivorous animals that eat these
plants
and they gain the energy which has
essentially come from sunlight and then
you have carnivorous animals that eat
those herbivorous animals and that's
where how the energy is transferred
through you know through these processes
so yeah it would be great if you could
achieve artificial or or
discover
how to
do photosynthesis artificially but we
are not there so
long way to go for that to happen
alpha says maybe life on earth is an
experiment that's why they visit us to
see the progress
interesting uh
interesting conjecture you make here my
friend
so um
what if life on earth is an experiment
see there are people you know what they
do they create these artificial
ecosystems they take a big jar they put
soil in there they put some plants in
there they put some i don't know
earthworms or whatever
and some water they seal this thing
and they expose it to sunlight 12 hours
a day or something like that eight hours
a day
or whatever and such ecosystems can be
kept sealed for decades
i remember i had seen somewhere a guy
who had this closed sealed off ecosystem
in a glass jar that was around for so
that was sealed for 60 plus years then
it was a thriving ecosystem you had
plants growing inside and you had some
bugs and things like that and generation
upon generation of these plants and
creatures insects etc were growing and
thriving in this closed sealed ecosystem
similarly our planet the earth is
one such sealed off ecosystem it's like
a massive giant glass jar
yeah sealed off by the vacuum of space
there is this atmosphere we have this
nice atmosphere
um that extends
hundreds of kilometers well the edge of
space is technically defined as three is
100 kilometers
above the surface but that's how it is
so you have this atmosphere you have a
significant amount of water and you have
all this soil topsoil the earth's crust
and all that and there could be
something going on
beneath the surf surface of the earth as
well
this massive ecosystem
and it's been evolving
for
four and a half billion years yeah
uh and life did emerge around three
point eight three point seven seven
billion years before today so what if
somebody came from elsewhere and seeded
life put the seeds of life on our planet
um there is a possibility that that
there is obviously the theory of panzer
murmur that panspermia that life was
seeded on our planet from somewhere else
maybe life the seeds of life exist
throughout space throughout the galaxy
throughout the universe and once in a
while they
they appear on a planet maybe
on an asteroid or comet and that's the
impact of the asteroid comet that brings
the seeds of life to the planet and
somehow that's how life is sparked off
on planets that can sustain this sort of
life carbon by based life yeah that's a
possibility or maybe there's an even
more interesting possibility that maybe
it is uh alien civilizations that want
to seed planets and
you know
put the seeds of of life on various
planets and maybe it's an experiment and
maybe we don't know they are there but
they are there and they're watching us
and sometimes they make their appearance
and then appear in the form of ufos or
whatever right
yeah it is possible
it is possible
uh there's this famous science fiction
book by arthur c clarke uh what is it
called 2001 a space odyssey i think it's
a trilogy or something and i remember
reading it a long time ago and in the
prologue of one of these things there
was this
yeah it was not a seeding of life but it
was the seeding of intelligent into a
intelligence into apes you know by
exposing them to something or other yeah
so it's a possibility but do we have any
evidence of that we don't have any
evidence of that
but
you can't discount the possibility even
though the probability is quite low it's
still a non-zero probability so maybe
somebody here from out there seeded life
maybe dna dna the dna molecule is is
incredibly complex and every single life
form on earth has dna so the key
the common factor in all life on the
planet is dna
yes every single life form has a certain
dna i mean it has dna
and the dna molecule differs there are
different sets of genes on each organism
which makes them different from each
other it's the genetic blueprint for
that species
and yes every single species whether
it's unicellular or multicellular or
higher life form or a very evolved life
former like us we all have dna we are
essentially carriers of dna
we are essentially living
bags
and our singular purpose is to pass on
the dna from generation to generation
yeah so maybe we believe that our life's
purpose is to i don't know whatever the
purpose of life is according to
philosophers and whatnot
self-help experts and all that but maybe
the actual biological purpose of life is
just to pass on dna from one generation
to another another and ensure that dna
survives
so maybe this dna was seeded into onto
our planet by some alien life by alien
civilization
possibility it's non-zero it's always a
possibility but the probability
obviously it's remote because we don't
have any evidence for this
so yes there are all these conjectures
and maybe some there could be some truth
to some of these but we don't quite know
yeah because we have never found any
unambiguous evidence of aliens
aliens
right so that's what we can see about
this matter as of now
swapnil again researchers at the
university of glasgow recently suggested
that water might have actually come from
the most unlikely source of all the sun
did water crash into the earth from
space by way of a massive comet or was
it around long before our planet's
formation
yes
so i am not aware of this um recent
piece of news but he's
recently suggested okay
uh
that water might have actually come from
the from the sun now let me try to think
about
how water could have come from the sun
the sun as we know it's it's mostly
hydrogen and a little bit of helium and
trace amounts of other other
elements there is no way molecular
water can survive there so how how would
water could have come from the sun what
we do know is that the sun gives off
this massive amount of solar wind it
ejects expels all this plasma from its
uh
from its atmosphere the sun has an
atmosphere it ejects the solar wind
maybe the solar wind could interact with
asteroids and comets and
produce water is there a way it could
happen i don't know i'll have to look at
the uh the the research paper so let me
not try to speculate because i've not
read it yet now
the question is how did water appear on
earth
see the solar system
formed
four point something four and a half or
slightly more than that billion years
ago
from a protostellar disc which is a disc
like structure very very hot yeah
it it uh coalesces slowly under its own
gravity at the center you have the
formation of a star and nuclear fusion
ignites
and then around the
around the protostar you have this big
collection of debris swirling around and
that too coarses coalesces under gravity
under self-gravitation and that's how
planets are formed and sometimes you
have collisions in the early solar
system early stellar systems you have
various collisions until things
stabilize a little bit and then you have
all these fields of debris and the thing
is this
this proto-stellar disc arises out of
gas clouds that exist before a star is
born now these gas clouds typically come
from the death of older stars
yes so the protocellular disc that gave
rise to the solar system that we live in
it came from the death of a star
that lived long before our sun existed
yeah so our sun is maybe a second
generation or even third generation star
yeah
now
the
gas disk or the gas cloud
that
existed and gave rise to over solar
system typically would have come from
the
from the death of a star older star in
the form of a supernova explosion
supernova explosions they give off lots
of uh
heavier elements
uh this iron in there and all kinds of
stuff right
now
what we do know
is that
so so what we know is that everything we
see around us everything in our body is
star star material star stuff it was all
born inside it in the it was all forged
in the furnace of an ancient star
everything inside our body everything
around us around us was forged in
ancient stellar furnaces deep inside the
nuclear fusion reaction that's how it
all came
and
these old stars would have had planets
most likely and water could have
abounded on those planets yeah
so the material that gave birth to the
solar system it looks like there was a
lot of water on it most of i mean even
today when these asteroids they crash
onto the planet especially a certain
type a certain class of asteroid called
carboniferous chondrites i think that's
what it's called so if you ex if you
take a cross section of these meteor
meteorites and you analyze them you find
that there is about three to twenty
percent water
in these meteorites right
so what is believed the well
most popular
uh
theory the consensus theory is that in
the very early phase of the solar system
when the earth was very new there was
this massive bombardment on the earth
bombardment of ancient asteroids yes and
that is what brought in
all the water of the earth that's what
gave earth its oceans so all the water
or most of it came from this asteroid
bombardment
and uh some of some of it could have
come from comets as well typically if
you look at the isotopic composition of
comets the deuterium to hydrogen ratio
uh
if you if you you can analyze that or it
in comets by taking spectra by using
spectrometers so i think they had
analyzed the the
deuterium to hydrogen ratio on various
comets that k that passed by the earth
recently 1990s and all that comet hail
bob yakutake etc and they found that the
deuterium to hydrogen ratio
in those spectrometer readings
was
twice that you find on in the earth's
oceans
so that that would indicate that if if
that is typical of most comets then most
likely it is not comets that gave us our
water right or maybe they gave us only a
small amount of the water that we have
on the other hand when you see the when
you analyze these the the
deuterium to hydrogen ratio on
carboniferous chondrites these
meteorites you find it very similar to
that in the ocean of the earth so that
is a strong indicator that most likely
it is this carboniferous contracts that
bombarded the early earth in very large
numbers and most likely they it is
meteorites this bombardment this heavy
bombardment that gave
earth the earth its oceans and all the
water yeah so that's what we know we
know there is water on on comets comets
are like dirty
uh snowballs
a snowball
lots of ice here
crystalline crystalline ice mixed with
dust and things like that so comets do
have water but asteroids also have water
and most likely the earth's water came
from
asteroids right so that's what we know
that's the best theory that we have
arjun sinha says
how
how does sharon curve radiation make
particles travel faster than light
um it's it's it's the other way around
it is the traveling of particles faster
than light within a certain medium that
gives rise to cherenkov radiation so the
shearing of radiation doesn't make
particles travel faster than light it is
the faster than light travel of
particles
within a certain medium that gives off
that that causes the this radiation to
be emitted
okay let's take a look at look at
cherenkov radiation what does it look
like
it's a blue
glow let me put that on the screen
cherenkov radiation
what exactly is this we'll get into it
in a moment
so cheering curve radiation is typically
something you see nuclear reactors
can you see this this blue glow
yes blue glow again it's typically this
bluish glow in nuclear reactors and
that's what we call cherenkov radiation
now what is this sharing of radiation
does it make particles trouble faster
than light or is it the
faster than light travel
of particles that gives off cheering
conversation so here's how it is
uh
the speed limit in the universe is the
speed of light
nearly 300 000 kilometers per second yes
uh that's the speed of light now
when it comes to
so this is in outer space in the vacuum
of space that's where light travels at
the speed
but
in
other media let's say the earth's
atmosphere or glass or water
in these media
light travels at a slower speed because
of the interaction of the photons with
the molecules of the medium right so in
nuclear reactors typically you have this
reactor which is immersed in water for
cooling purposes and so on right
now the nuclear fission reaction
that is typically what you see that is
not typically that's always what you see
in earth
in in nuclear reactors created by humans
the nuclear fission reaction gives off
this energetic
fast moving particles
and
what you find is that these are very
fast moving particles and they break the
speed of light limit in water
so light in water travels at 75 percent
the speed of light in vacuum
approximately 75
of the speed of light in vacuum but
these energetic particles given off by
the nuclear fission reaction they travel
faster than the speed of light in water
but they can't break the speed limit of
light in vacuum okay so understand that
it's faster than the speed of light only
in water
so this creates
a shock wave
a conical shock wave of light
that travels uh that comes after the the
particle has passed you by it's like the
the
it's like the shock wave
it's like the shock wave or or sonic
boom produced by an aircraft that's
traveling faster than the speed of light
in in the speed of speed of sound
in the atmosphere let's say you have a
fighter plane let's say you're talking
about the tejus fighter plane right
uh the fiji's fighter plane is a
supersonic fighter plane so it takes off
it flies in the air and at some point in
its travel it goes supersonic it crosses
the mach one limit it crosses the sound
barrier so when this happens
the sound waves produced
by the plane they they they are trailing
in the wake of the plane because the
plane is for traveling faster than the
speed of light uh sound so that produces
this conical uh conical shock wave
that hits you only after the plane is
gone so when the plane is coming towards
you supersonically at this point further
faster than the speed of sound you hear
nothing it's only when the after the
plane passes you by that you hear this
shock wave right this big
shock wave uh let's see i'm sure there
is some illustration of that over here
yeah this is the kind of shockwave that
you have that you have
uh yeah there he goes speed of sound
supersonic and all that
so that is a sonic shockwave cherenkov
radiation is the light equivalent of
that sonic shock wave
right so that is sharing of radiation so
let's say you have an electron that's
passing through
water
uh faster than the speed of light in
then it will the interaction of this
electron with the light with the water
molecules gives off this very high
energy very high very high frequency
radiation that is typically in the blue
end of the spectrum of the light
spectrum
and when you have this process ongoing
on a regular basis in a nuclear reactor
the entire water glows blue right so
that is what cherenkov radiation is
it doesn't make particles travel faster
than light it is the result of particles
traveling faster than light in water or
in any other medium you can have some a
similar kind of effect in in air also
i'm sure
not that i know of it but it's certainly
possible yeah so that is what sharing
cooperation is a very interesting effect
it is named after a russian
physicist mr cherenkov
okay vinu says what is the evidence for
the big bang theory how do we know the
big bang happened
how do we know the universe is thirteen
point seven thirteen point eight thirty
point seven seven whatever 13.8 billion
years old
yeah
how do we know the big bang happened
what is the evidence for the big bang
so
so what's the evidence for the big bang
there are two pieces of evidence that
make the most well which are the
strongest pieces of evidence one is the
cmb the cosmic microwave background that
is radiation that is the
after glow so called supposedly of the
big bang and then you have the
cosmological redshift distance relation
the the hubble relation right so these
are the two pieces of evidence that
provide the strongest support for the
big bang theory so what is the big bang
theory the big bang theory says that the
universe
originated as as a point
in the very beginning the universe was
just a point
uh
you could call it the big bang
singularity and something made it expand
the space time but then it expand and
that's what created the universe so how
do we know this
why did people propose the big bang
theory so in the 19 early 20th century
in the 1920s or so edwin hubble
the american astronomer he he discovered
that the universe is expanding that the
galaxies that we observe are all red
shifted which means that you have this
uh doppler effect kind of thing
happening and the universe the galaxies
are traveling away from us and the uh
the
expansion is actually accelerating right
and that is the the redshift distance
relation the hubble constant
uh so
if you
if we know that the universe is
expanding
the expansion is accelerating then we
can extrapolate that back in time so
right now if the universe is getting
bigger in the past it would have been
smaller and smaller and if you calculate
it it gives you and the calculations
have been refined over the decades and
now we know that the universe began
around almost 13.8 billion years before
today that is the best uh
estimate or or calculation that we have
right
now again if the universe was infinite
almost infinitely dense or maybe
infinitely dense and then it expanded
then
you would have had certain properties
that the universe would have had
for instance
in the very beginning the universe was
just pure energy just pure energy then
something called inflation happened
and it gave birth to mass
so the energy that was uh
that that condensed in the form of mass
but in even then after the inflation if
inflationary epoch you had a very dense
very hot universe
so you had photons and you had the very
early uh
subatomic subatomic particles you had
this plasma in the universe now think
about it this way
think of the sun
we know the sun is a very hot very very
hot ball of matter yeah all the hydrogen
fusing into helium that sort of fusion
reaction is happening in the core of the
sun
these photons are born out of the
nuclear fusion reaction all right it
gives off photons of light these are
actually gamma-ray photons that are born
in the
core of the sun
now when we think of the sun we think of
a very luminous object
very hot very bright
but these photons that emerge from the
sun they take more than a hundred
thousand years to travel from the core
of the sun to the outside and that's
that's how they're emitted so every
single light photon that we observe
has
was born in the core of the sun maybe a
hundred thousand years ago maybe a
million or more years ago
it takes that long for that photon to
journey out of the sun
now imagine the universe as desert as
the sun it was at one point in time so
the photons
had a very small mean free path they
were constantly bumping into these
subatomic particles and all that and
there was no light which means that
inside the sun there is no light
the light is only outside the sun
the sun is luminous on the outside
inside the sun it's all dark
because the photons aren't able to move
around they're constantly being bumping
into other particles and being emitted
and reabsorbed and emitted and all that
so it's actually kind of dark inside the
sun it's on the outside that it's
shining in luminous
so the early universe was like that it's
only around
about uh
between 240 to 300 thousand years before
today after the big bang that the first
light was able to emerge when the
universe cooled down sufficiently for uh
hydrogen atoms to form for them to
capture electrons and for stable
hydrogen atoms to form it's only then
that photons became free to travel and
that's when you had the first light in
the universe right so that's what the
calculations tell us
that should have happened between 240
000 and 300 000 years after the big bang
so if this theory is right those photons
should still be around
yes in in the very beginning the photons
were very energetic very hot but as the
universe expanded if it happened it is
it is it expanded it must have cooled
down so the photons would have been red
shifted stretched out their wavelengths
would have stretched out and they would
have lost energy and according to the
the calculations they should be now in
the
millimeter range i believe right
millimeter of
range
so we do observe these photons these
cosmic microwave background photons uh
there was a kobe experiment in the 19 19
what 1980s 1980s 1990s then there was a
wmap experiment a wmap observatory
wilkinson microwave an isotope an
isotropy
uh whatever project or whatever it is
yeah the map
so
this is a microwave this is microwave
edition not millimeter edition microwave
radiation uh and so on yeah so we then
we had the the planck observatory which
went which was operational about a
decade and a half or so ago so all of
these various experiments have shown us
i've demonstrated that the cosmic
microwave background the left over
after glow of the first light of the big
after the big bang
still exists
and it's it's very
low temperature radiation
its temperature is about
2.725 or something kelvin just a little
bit above absolute zero yeah very cold
light in the future as the billions of
years progress it's gonna get even
colder yeah it's gonna lose even more
energy because of red shifting and all
so all of these pieces of evidence tell
us that the big bang actually happened
otherwise they would not see these
things right so you have the
cosmological redshift distance relation
and the cosmic microbial background so
these two are the major pieces of
evidence
that that provide the strongest support
for the big bang theory there are there
have been other other theories doctor
john narliker had this theory called
hoyle narliker which was a form of
steady state universe that the universe
is eternal and unchanging that sort of
thing but well the observational
evidence doesn't support that the
observational evidence supports the big
bang theory what we call the big bang
theory so that in brief is the evidence
for the big bang theory that's how we
know that this the big bang actually
most likely happened and that's how we
know because of the calculations that
the universe is approximately 13.7
billion years old
rtk says
there are some scientists who say that
the big bang isn't the beginning of the
universe it's actually the end of some
other universe if it's true does it mean
that the previous universe was
contracting at the rate at which the
previous universe is expanding
um
see
the evidence the observational evidence
that we have
is is limited not it tells us that a big
bang kind of thing would have happened
so
based on all the evidence that we have
the best evidence that we have we have
constructed this theory of the origin
and the history of the universe which we
call the big bang cosmological theory
right
um
so
it says that in the past the universe
was contracted into this tiny tiny
little point
the big bang singularity and right now
it's expanding so yes there are theories
that say that maybe we had a
there was a universe before the big bang
maybe there's a bounce big bounce kind
of thing a universe exp expands and then
starts contracting and it contracts back
into a point
so-called big crunch
but it just doesn't stay as a point it
bounces back again so that's a big
bounce that's a kind of cyclical
universe kind of thing yeah and then you
have the
uh roger penrose theory of eons
cosmological eons
so
uh
the expansion of the universe it gives
rise to the birth of a new universe that
sort of thing yeah so we have these
theories but uh thus far these are just
theories or just hypothesis more or less
because uh
a theory has to be falsifiable a
scientific theory has to be falsifiable
and thus far we don't have any means of
either proving or disproving these
theories right
i think roger penrose did give some kind
of indication as to how one could test
the theory that could be ripples from an
earlier universe left left behind in our
universe or something like that but yeah
we are still far from doing that
but it is certainly a possibility
it is certainly a possibility that that
could have been our universe before our
own
yeah
every universe has a certain timeline as
a certain lifetime and eventually it uh
either contracts again the expansion
after a point stops and it goes into a
contraction kind of thing and it goes
back into the big bang singularity and
then it once again
that's a possibility but we don't know
for sure
yeah so we have people are working on
various theories and if some evidence
emerges then one could take one of these
theories more seriously than the others
uh so yeah some physicists speculate
that the big bang isn't the beginning of
the universe but there is no proof thus
far but it's something that one should
certainly
consider seriously because it certainly
does fit into the laws of physics yeah
it's possible
karthik srinivas says is hd140283
methuselah star older than the universe
well it's a star okay what is this
methuselah star
it is a
star that is
located about
190 light years from here from the earth
from our solar system so it's not really
very far it's essentially in our
galactic neighborhood in our corner of
the galaxy more or less
yeah it's not far the galaxy is massive
so
this star
is is somewhat blue shifted which
indicates that it's moving towards us
rather than going away from us and it's
just 190 kilometers from 190
light years from the earth
now um
so this star i believe has been known
for a century or more
and various calculations have been done
as to
figure out how exactly how far it is
from earth using the parallax method and
various other methods and what we know
is that this is a
this is an
iron deficient star
this star has very low abundances of the
heavier elements like iron etc which
kind of indicates
that it was born it was formed in the
very early universe when the heavier
elements hadn't been formed so how do
they how are the heavier elements formed
they are formed in the end stages or
later stages of nuclear fusion in
massive stars
but in the very early universe you would
not have had these massive stars see
the first stars in the universe
uh
emerged when the universe was about a
hundred million years old the first
light in the universe was
a quarter of a million years after the
big bang
the first stars were born about 100
million years after the big bang and the
first galaxies came about 330 million
years after the big bang the oldest
galaxy that has been found it was
discovered by the james webb space
telescope it's called glass z13
it's believed to be about 330 million
years uh it was believed to have formed
about 330 millions of years after big
bang
now
so the first stars emerged a hundred
million years after the big bang and
it's only after these stars would have
died that the heavier elements like iron
etc would have been spewed out in
supernova
explosions into
into space into interstellar space and
it's only the second generation stars
that would have been
uh richer
in these heavier elements so this star
the methuselah star is a star that is
very deficient in heavy elements which
indicates it's one of the first stars to
be born in the universe and the various
calculations have shown that it's either
17 billion years old or 14 point
something billion years old or 13.7
billion years old so it's either older
than the universe
or as old as the universe
and that's a big mystery because how can
anything be older than the new universe
especially when this star is part of
our universe
so yeah it is a big mystery and thus far
it has not been resolved if you look at
the star it's kind of bluish let's take
a look at what it looks like
methuselah m-e-t-h-u-s-e
i don't know where these names come from
but whatever
mitchus
what's it look like it looks bluish
and why is it look bluish because it is
uh blue shifted it's kind of moving
towards us yeah
so this is the star that's which is a
great abiding
mystery
all the calculations
uh and how do you calculate how old it
is you first
figure out how far it is from the earth
from the solar system you do it through
a variety of methods and then you figure
out the the luminosity of the star which
kind of tells you uh
gives you various things so that's how
you you calculate this thing right
so the distance and luminosity is
luminosity tell you
of give you various indications
about the star the data yep so this star
is a big mystery
all the
best calculations say that it's either
older than the universe or as old as the
universe certainly it certainly predates
the first stars
that were born in the universe and why
is it so we still don't know so it's one
of the big mysteries in astronomy and
astrophysics and that's why it is the
subject of significant research
dr nishte gongay says why shouldn't we
look directly at a solar eclipse is it
harmful in any way
please comment about lunar eclipses as
well
okay firstly lunar eclipses and solar
eclipses are very different yeah what is
a lunar eclipse the lunar eclipse is
when the earth's shadow falls on the
moon and completely eclipses it so the
entire moon goes black goes dark right
so that comes that happens when the
earth comes between the sun and the moon
which is something that happens much
more frequently than a solar eclipse
yeah so a lunar eclipse is essentially
the earth's shadow falling on the moon
which is when the earth comes between
the uh the moon and the sun that's a
lunar eclipse it's perfectly fine to
look at the lunar eclipse it's not going
to hurt your eyes in any way whatsoever
right so next time there's a lunar
eclipse go out there and take a look
enjoy it's fun to watch
now what's a solar eclipse
a solar eclipse is much more rare
rarer
a solar eclipse is when the moon
comes between
where you are on the planet and the sun
so it is the moon's shadow falling on
the earth
now the moon's shadow is quite fast so
solar eclipse lasts only for a few
minutes and then the solar eclipse goes
away
so if you are fortunate enough to be in
the
path of the totality of the eclipse
that's when you are able to see a
complete
a full solar eclipse otherwise you will
only see a partial solar eclipse now
here's the thing
um
it is actually
i be careful when i say this and when
and and i i request none of you to try
it
but
when you you have the totality of the
solar eclipse when the sun is completely
eclipsed by the moon it's actually safe
to look at it
uh with naked eyes yeah however
the problem with these solar eclipses is
that they are very brief
and
it may catch you by surprise that the
moon suddenly moves out of the way and
the full sunlight comes at you right so
the sun's light is extremely bright
it's very harmful
um
as kids i think most of us we we do this
silly thing of trying to look at the sun
i surely did that i suddenly did that
when i was a kid you know less than 10
years old looking staring at the sun and
trying to see trying to see if i can
look at the sun yeah and when you do
that you have this natural reflex of the
eyes you know try to close auto
involuntarily you may try to keep them
open but they're closed right they close
at least halfway so that shields you
from the radiation of the sun and
secondly the pupils of the eyes they
contract to pinpricks so that ensures
that very little sunlight comes into the
eyes so even as a kid if you're trying
to look at the sun you have all these
defense mechanisms the protections that
ensure that you don't suffer any real
damage to your to your retina
because the sun's light the radiation is
extremely intense very bright it can
destroy the retina that that's behind
the eye right behind the pupil of the
eye at the other side the other side of
the of the eyeball
and if you do that you're gonna have
permanent damage now when you're looking
at the solar eclipse in it let's say
it's a full solar eclipse so the sun has
gone completely dark
if you're doing that then first of all
your eyes are not you know squeezed half
shut like that and secondly your pupils
are fully open
they're fully open they're allowing the
maximum amount of light to go into your
retina
and then
if
by the the moon surprises you and just
moves out of the way and you the the
first uh
rays of light coming out of the sun full
stream
then you will find yourself caught
underwears your eyes are fully open
and your pupils are fully dilated and
they are allowing the maximum amount of
light to come in and that's when you
will suffer permanent damage in your
retina it may it may cause blindness or
partial blindness you don't want that to
happen right
so that's how it is so even though it is
safe
for a few minutes to look at the
completely occluded sun when the solar
eclipse is full not partial it is still
highly dangerous and completely another
and unadvisable to do that
so either look at a solar necklace by
seeing the reflection of the sun in
there are a variety of ways of doing it
but if you are actually going to stare
at the sun with your own eyes you need
to use those dark glasses or whatever
the standard equipment the
standard equipment that is provided for
seeing a solar eclipse that's typically
very thick dark glasses right so that's
what happens
the sun's rays are extremely energetic
very bright there's a whole amount of
there's a whole spectrum of radiation
that comes in you know
the far the far infrared infrared right
light also which is very which is almost
like ionizing radiation and all that
so all of that is going to destroy your
eyes if you try to do this so please
don't do it
please do not do it at all don't ever
try it
alpha beta says why do wrinkles appear
we can can we be old without having
wrinkles too
wrinkles uh appear on a human being's
skin
it's it's the because of the process of
aging
so if you have an infant the skin is
very very flexible very very soft here
and very healthy
but as a human being ages
you know past a certain age
the wrinkles appear because of a number
of reasons first of all the skin becomes
less
flexible
less stretchable stretchable that is
number one secondly the the natural oils
that the skin typically
gives off
the skin especially the face is
typically a little bit oily right
some people are have more oily some skin
some people have less oily skin but the
skin it gives off these natural oils and
that also contributes to keeping the
skin flexible stretchable and and
healthy and young
so as a person ages firstly this the
flexibility of the skin decreases
secondly the amount of oil that is
emitted by the skin
that also decreases
and thirdly the amount of fat that is
below the surface of the skin you know
that also kind of decreases so all of
these factors contribute to these
wrinkles appearing on on
not just a person's face but the
hands and whatever else right so yeah
that's that's how it happens
it's all because of the process of aging
now the process of aging aging
how it happens it is believed to be
because of the shortening of the
telomeres at the ends of your
chromosomes
so inside your cells not the red blood
cells but the other cells you have these
chromosomes that contain your genetic
blueprint the dna right and at the ends
of the chromosomes you have something
called telomeres so these telomeres uh
as the cell division happens again and
again and again and again which is
natural in a healthy body
every time cell division happens the
telomeres are shortened a little bit and
it is believed that the shortening of
the telomeres at the ends of the
chromosomes that is what contributes to
the process of aging right and there is
also this research that's happening in
into how to reverse or either either
reverse or or at least stop the
lengthening of the telomeres
and that could possibly uh
help ward off aging or delay aging at
least yeah that's the kind of research
that's that's the hope that these
researchers have i mean who doesn't want
to live forever or at least live to 150
or 200 right that would be great some
people think so yeah
so anyway the wrinkles they appear
because of these reasons not the maybe
the telomere lengthening or shortening
shortening actually could contribute to
it but over time
as the years go by the flexibility and
stretchability of the skin decreases it
becomes more brittle
the amount of oil that's exuded by the
skin also decreases that also
contributes to more brittleness and more
inflexibility of the skin and the amount
of fat that's at the subcutaneous level
also
decreases in all of these factors
contribute to the appearance of wrinkles
which become
more pronounced
with age
right that's the natural progression of
how
wrinkles appear on people's skin
so the question is can we be old without
having wrinkles i have no idea
i don't know
it's part of aging so it's just how it
is so maybe in the future scientists
will invent some some
some mechanism by which the aging
process could be
slowed down or stopped altogether or
maybe even reversed who knows
maybe there'll be some skin oil skin
cream or maybe some
tablet to take out some gene therapy or
whatever so yeah in the future this sort
of thing may happen
but as of today i don't think it's
possible to get old without having
wrinkles uh
every person who ages will develop some
amount of wrinkles i suppose yeah
that's just how it is
swapnil again
what are brain pools how are they made
and where are they located in the oceans
if sea creatures are able to survive in
them could it give
astrobiologists a hint
on how life could thrive on other worlds
okay let's see what brain pools look
like okay first of all what are brain
pools to answer what are brine pools we
must first answer what is brain
so brine is sea water with a very high
degree of salinity
i think what is the typical salinity
percentage of sea water
three percent salt
not sure okay don't quote me on another
on that but uh typically brine
is sea water with ten times that much
salinity so if on average sea water has
three percent salt three ppm of salt
then brine could have 30 ppm of salt or
maybe more than that maybe 50. so it's
very concentrated and very saline yeah
it's its salinity is way higher than
your typical regular salt water in the
oceans
so that is brine so what are brine poos
these are regions in the ocean at the
bottom of the oceans where you have a
collection of brine
so brine is is
this water with extremely high salinity
much higher than the rest of the ocean
and because of the extremely high
salinity salinity it is much denser
than ocean water and that's why it
congregates in one place and it forms
these pools that create indentations on
the ocean floors so it's like a lake
it's like a lake
on the ocean floor a lake of brain on
the ocean floor right so let's take a
look at what
these things look like if they we have
examples brine
brine pool
let's see what a brine pool looks like
and let's put that on the screen
image
okay here's an example of a brine pool
as you can see it's like a lake on the
bottom of the ocean
under water lakes of despair they're
called so these are lakes and they
actually look like craters because the
brine is much denser and therefore it
creates these depressions on the ocean
floor
and yeah you can look at you can see the
color is different and it just looks
different from regular ocean water
now
one of the things about brine first of
all we know we know it's extremely
saline its salinity is very high
secondly it also
is anoxic
so because of the extreme salinity it
also becomes the water also becomes
anoxic what is anoxic water it means
water with very little dissolved oxygen
so if you have if you see various kinds
of marine life whether it is fish
whether it is crustaceans crabs lobsters
prawns shrimps whatever
they all live
by by extracting the dissolved oxygen
out of the ocean ocean water and they
use it they do it through these organs
called gills right gills
now if an organism like let's say a crab
or a fish were to go and swim into a
brine pool they would immediately find
that there is very little oxygen here
and the serenity is very high and if
they stay there for more than a few
seconds
they will go into hypoxia which means
that brain will stop receiving uh oxygen
and they will die so typically you find
lots of dead animals marine animals fish
crustaceans etc inside brine pools and
that's why they call them what are these
pools of despair or whatever
so any any uh sea animal sea creature
that goes into it will almost
instantaneously
die
so that is what the what you have in
brain poles but on the on the edges of
these brain pulse you have certain kinds
of life
certain organisms that are called
extremophiles
yeah
that that undergo chemosynthesis so we
have photosynthesis in which
light
is used to create
various uh forms of energy chemical
energy yeah so chemosynthesis is when
this sort of
reaction happens without
the need for light
that's chemosynthesis so you have
extremophile animals that can live on
the edges
of brine pools but not inside blind
pools right
so that's what it is so the question is
how do these brine pools how are they
made how do they form
i believe how brine pools are formed how
is brine formed inside oceans
i think it happens in cold regions of
the ocean so when uh
on the surface of the ocean
when you have very low temperatures
below below freezing temperatures that's
when the
ocean waters freeze you have the
formation of icebergs and ice sheets etc
etc right
in the polar and antarctic regions of
the of the earth and in cold latitude
yes you have this happening so when
water freezes and becomes ice
the salt molecules aren't able to become
a part of the crystalline ice structure
the ice crystals
so there is this process called salt
rejection i think
so when the water freezes salt is
rejected
so these ice
structures they are less saline
than the actual ice the actual ocean
water so all of this
salt that is rejected
it goes back into the ocean and it forms
brine
and that's how the brine is formed and
that's how then the brine is denser than
the ocean water that's why it sinks to
the bottom of the oceans and in some
places you have the big collection of
collections of brine and that's what
these brine pools are
so yeah that's the answer and if sea
creatures are able to survive in them
could it give astrobiologists a life a
hint on how life could thrive on other
worlds possibly possibly yeah
astrobiologists are always on the
lookout for strange forms of life on our
planet
we have various extremophile organisms
such as at deep sea vents when you have
these uh
these essentially these volcanic
openings on the seafloor
which give which which give rise to very
very strange biology in in those regions
yeah life that can thrive without
sunlight extremophile life so similarly
around
brine pools we have these uh
organisms that undergo chemo synthesis
chemosynthesis yeah these are also
extremophile creatures that also could
give some some hints as to how what kind
of life could thrive in extreme
environments yeah so
certainly something that they would want
to study
pulkit says how is a black hole
formed do you think there's a possible
end to it or is it just like a space
animal with never ending with never
ending hunger
if there's any what impact could it
create in space in the last stages of
its death okay how is a black hole
formed your typical regular stellar mass
black holes
they are formed at the end stage of a
supernova eruption explosion yeah so
let's say you have this massive star
let's say it's 20 times the mass of the
sun 50 times the mass of the sun massive
star it uh in the end stage it
collapses upon itself yeah
and this collapse
gives rise to an explosion the supernova
explosion but at the very core of the
star you're going to have these crushing
gravitational forces that will repel any
of the electron degeneracy pressure or
any other thing that can
you know
keep it off and that's how it causes
this this collapse of the star a region
of over density that is too dense for
even light to escape and that's what
creates a black hole that's what gives
rise to a black hole in some cases
we find that stars possibly collapse
into black holes without ever reaching
the supernova stage
you know there are these old star maps
star images that are taken over the
decades and sometimes we find the stars
have just disappeared
stars that were shining
let's say in the 1970s 1980s today if
you look at the same part of the sky
that star no longer is there it's just
winked off
yeah so maybe it's a star that collapsed
directly into a black hole so typically
it's because of this yeah the end stage
of a star's life or
actually the end stage of a star's death
that's what gives rise to a black hole
when the star the the nuclear fusion
reaction is no longer able to uh
continue and the entire mass of the star
collapses upon its core
and that is the core collapse
typically there's a supernova but
sometimes by some reaction by some
mechanism you may have collapsed
directly into a black hole
so that is your typical
stellar mass black hole that's how it is
formed
um
super super massive black holes because
we don't quite know how they are formed
because for a black hole to become that
large it would take a time that is
longer than the actual age of the
universe so super massive black holes
the formation mechanism is kind of a
mystery
you typically have a supermassive black
hole at the center of every galaxy most
galaxies our own galaxy has a massive
supermassive black hole at its center
and so on so how they are formed they
it is speculated that they
it was primordial black holes that
formed the seeds of supermassive black
holes that's that's a possibility so
what are these primordial black holes
primordial black holes are black holes
that could have
formed in the very early universe as
regions of over densities here
uh because of quantum fluctuations in
the very early universe
so those would be typically microscopic
black holes mbh or pbhs primordial black
holes
uh and it's possible that they could
be a significant component of dark
matter today yeah
in in various forms
so that's how a black hole is formed is
there is it possible there's an n2 black
holes yes black holes
black holes of temperature they are
thermodynamic objects and anything that
has a temperature
radiates
it radiates radiation
so black holes uh radiate black body
radiation
and black holes over temperature that's
what they radiate
uh and this radiation is called hawking
radiation and it's essentially like a
process of evaporation yeah
and because of that black holes
typically become smaller over time as
they evaporate away their their
mass energy
so the black holes any black holes
temperature is inversely proportional
with size the larger the surface area
the lower the temperature so
supermassive black holes are typically
extremely cold even colder than the
uh
temperature of the cosmic microwave
background relation so in a sense
supermassive black holes can never die
because they're actually accreting
mass rather than rather than
emitting radiation because they are at a
temperature that's lower than the
ambient temperature but smaller black
holes are hotter and they would emit
hawking radiation which says that every
black hole is a certain life span
you can calculate the lifespan quite
easily actually if you if you know
if you know the physics yeah so every
black hole has a certain lifespan life
span
you can calculate that
and eventually
as the black hole becomes smaller it
becomes hotter as it becomes hot becomes
hotter it radiates faster
it becomes even smaller so the end stage
of a black hole's life is a massive
explosion boom
so black holes die
in explosions
that's what the theory tells us we have
never seen these explosions thus far
but it's possible that it is the end
stage eruption or explosion
of the hawking radiation of a black
hole's end stage life that could be
the the
the progenitor of certain classes of of
ultra high energy cosmic rays
it's possible
it is indeed a possibility
so that's what that's the kind of uh
life cycle a black hole has there is
certainly a possible end to black holes
in their lives yeah
so
yeah so what what impact would it create
in space at
the last stages of its death it would be
a big flash of radiation flash of light
and things spewing out of it at very at
relativistic velocities it could be
possibly something that gives rise to
the so the the gamma-ray bursts possibly
gamma ray bursts
and so on yeah
avinash singh says if i enter into a
black hole
if i enter a black hole
will the time stop for me as soon as i
cross the event horizon or does the time
stop after i reach or when i reach the
singularity
if time stops just after crossing the
event horizon does it mean
wouldn't it mean that i'll be stuck at
the event horizon and will not reach the
singularity because when time stops
nothing can move from its place okay
what happens
so we have to understand time dilation
which is a an effect of
relativity
dilation is something you study when
you're studying special relativity but
it's something that you experience
because of
mass and velocity and all that
so the concept is very simple
the faster you go the slower your time
is but you will not sense time slowing
down for you time goes on the same
let's say you have twins
two two brothers twin brothers one is on
earth and one goes into on into space on
a rocket
yeah at a relativistic velocity let's
say half the speed of light yeah
so we we put two
identical clocks with these two twins
the same clock one with the twin on the
rocket and one with the twin on the
earth
and our friend on the rocket he goes
away
and he has this clock which tells him
that one year has elapsed and then after
one year is elapsed he comes back to the
earth and he will find that maybe 30 or
40 years on earth have elapsed so for
him only one year went by but for his
twin on on earth 30 or 40 years had
elapsed at the same time
so the clocks move differently
the rate at which time flows in the
rocket is different from the rate at
which time flows on the earth
it's very confusing but it's actually
quite simple
so
so if you are on earth you will ex you
will see that the time on the rocket is
is flowing very slowly as the rocket is
going very fast now
let's say you are falling into a black
hole
yeah
let's say you have two observers
let's say you have two two human beings
one human being is at a distance of
let's say
a thousand kilometers from the black
hole
in orbit around the black hole so this
person is in no danger of falling into
the black hole so he can observe what's
happening the other person which is you
my dear friend you're going into the
black hole
so let's say your friend
is in orbit around the black hole he's
not falling but he's going to observe
what happens to you and you are falling
into the black hole
now the presence of mass also slows time
down
so the closer you come to the black hole
the slower your time is
if you're wearing a watch for you the
time will pass just normally
but your friend who is sitting far away
will see your progress towards the black
hole slow down
and when you reach the event horizon
you
for your friend
who is sitting far away you will appear
to have frozen in time
he will never see you enter the black
hole
for your friend who's sitting far away
you will seem like you have just become
stuck to the event horizon and you're
not going any much any anywhere further
from there
but you actually will enter the event
horizon and you will go into the black
hole yeah so for you time doesn't stop
or time doesn't slow down but from the
perspective of a distant observer you
will slowly slowly slowly slowly stop
at the event horizon
now what happens to you when you come
inside the event horizon
so uh
once you enter once you cross the event
horizon and you move towards the
singularity it i think you will
experience all the future time of the
universe
until the end of the universe so before
you reach the singularity you will
experience all the future events or
something like that yeah so it's not
very well understood yet but yeah it's
kind of like that of course before that
you will die because you will be
stretched out into
spaghetti kind of thing so
so only in case you have an
indestructible
consciousness will you be able to
experience future time and all that
it's very weird and it's still not very
well understood because
as you go deeper towards the singularity
the mathematics of general relativity
breaks down and you have a singularity
here because which which obviously
should not exist because it is
unphysical
anyhow that's how it is so uh
for you who is entering the black hole
time doesn't stop time doesn't even slow
down for you it's just a few minutes and
you're in
and the smaller the black hole the more
the spaghettification if it's a super
massive black hole you will feel nothing
as you enter the event as you cross the
event horizon but if it is a smaller
black hole
long before you cross the event horizon
you'll be stretched out into spaghetti
and you would have died it's not a nice
death so that's how it is
dungar sinchohan says why is a black
hole cold called a hole it's just a
mountain of matter crushed into a tiny
space should they be renamed you know
what you can go ahead and rename it to
whatever you want these names black hole
big bang theory these are not scientific
names
typically these names are coined by by
non-science people typically by
journalists i think the the term black
hole was coined if i'm not mistaken by
some journalist
and then it stuck the term stuck and
then even scientists physicists started
using it and now that's what we call
them it's not really a hole right it's
it's a
well it's it's a
region of space that is so so dense that
light can't
exit from it
so it's not a hole it's it's it's just
pure mass essentially
uh yeah so it should not be called a
hole it's it's incorrect to call it a
hole in space time or whatever say
you want to rename it you can go ahead
and call it by some other name if you
wish to but it's it's the name that is
stuck because it's it's uh it is so
catchy black hole yeah and similarly big
bang theory was actually a federative
name
i think it was coined coined by fred
hoyle if i'm not mistaken to make fun of
this theory which was so outlandish
so he he coined this this term
big bang
to make fun of the theory
as a means of disrespecting the theory
but it it kind of stuck
and then this theory took off because it
it makes a lot of sense from all the
observational evidence that we have so
now it's called the big bang theory even
though it's not it was not a bank or an
explosion
it was not an explosion it was an
expansion of space time so that's how it
is sometimes you have all these weird
unscientific terms that stick and then
even scientists start using them yeah
so yeah if you want to rename black hole
to something more
appropriate you can go ahead and do that
and if it is catchy enough it may catch
on
okay dash plays says
does light bend towards the gravity or
does every wavelength of light bend
towards gravity
um
light in gravity has this
see what what happens is this
mass
curves
space time
curvature
we live in four dimensional space time
we experience the three dimensions of
space top down
uh
up down
backward forward and whatever right
three dimensions of space time this this
way
the three-dimensional coordinate
geometry that we experience in the real
world there's a fourth dimension which
is time which we experience very vaguely
so these four dimensions they form the
fabric of space time we cannot
imagine four dimensional
space time we can only imagine the world
in three dimensions but space time is in
four dimensions now if you have a mass
let's say a planet or a star
that
is going to warp and curve space time we
know the the the typical trampoline
image that they show us right uh curved
space time let me see
the space time
yeah the typical image that they show
you to illustrate how how this works let
me show you that
uh one second let me put that on the
screen
curved space time
so you know how it is right
it's like a trampoline in which you put
a mass a ball and that that curves the
trampoline surface and that is the
curvature of space time which actually
doesn't make much sense because we
you're seeing space time as a
two-dimensional thing a better way of
visualizing this
is by looking at this image
let me show you that
so this is the actual curvature of space
time right the entire
four you using curvature of spatial
space time in three dimensions here it's
actually four dimensions which you
cannot visualize but this is a better
way of looking at it so the mass the
presence of mass
curves and warps
the fabric of space-time itself
now if you have a beam of light that is
traveling straight
but then you have this mass sitting
there which you can see there there
there yeah
then the beam of light will not be able
to travel in a straight line it will
travel in a curved path because the
space itself is curved right and the
time itself is curved
so that's why
gravity
bends the path of light
and yes every wavelength of life light
is bent
it doesn't matter what what wavelength
the light has it it is all bent because
the the path itself is is curved let's
say imagine that the light is like a car
traveling on a road if the road is
straight the light will the the car will
travel straight but if the road is
curved then the car will have to travel
in a curved path that's how it is yeah
so
light is bent by gravity because
space-time itself is warped it is curved
it is bent by gravity and yes every
wavelength of light is curved is bent
it's its path is bent by gravity
dash plays again
does gravity of nt
matter
okay what is asking is
does antimatter
have repulsive gravity
right that's what is asking
so you have two kinds of matter you have
regular matter that we are made of yeah
and you have antimatter
so the question is does antimatter have
repulsive gravity or or negative gravity
which means that instead of falling up
it should fall down no that is not the
case because we have
manufactured very very small tiny
quantities of antimatter in labs yeah in
various colliders etc and it behaves
gravitationally just the same as regular
matter
so unfortunately antimatter doesn't have
the interesting property of having
ripples of gravity just has regular
gravity ripples of gravity we we haven't
found anything any substance that that
has that property yeah negative negative
mass or something like that yeah we
still haven't found that
avinash says if a distant solar system
is millions of light years away and so
we see it as it was millions of years
ago how can i see how can we see what it
looks like now simple answer we can't
see what it looks like now impossible
simply can't happen won't happen ever
unless you sit on a
spacecraft you travel all the way there
and then once you are there you can see
how it is right now
for your right now
but for for us over here it will be
different
yeah so you
you have this methuselah star which is
190 light years away so what we see of
it is what was happening 190 years ago
yeah
so there is absolutely no way
of seeing what it looks like right now
and the
the the concept of now
doesn't really make sense
in relativity
there is the relativity of simultaneity
which is a whole different thing so an
event
let's say two events occur
simultaneously to me
but for somebody else a lot large
distance away those two events may not
appear to be simultaneous
that is also a thing so now itself
doesn't make a lot of sense from the
perspective of general relativity yeah
the the concept of now
so yeah there's no way
for us sitting here
to see what something looks like right
now if it is millions of light years
away simply not possible
simply
okay venue says what are cosmic strings
what is their relationship with
wormholes
uh cosmic strings are hypothetical no
theoretical defects
in the fabric of space-time they are
called topological defects and they may
have been the result of the expansion
of space-time in the aftermath of what
we call the big bang you know
so these topological defects could have
been produced in great quantities
in the very early universe
so what are what do i mean by a
topological defect
yeah a defect in this fabric of
space-time it's like a wrinkle
in space-time we spoke about some
sometime ago wrinkles on people's skin
yeah wrinkles are these
these uh
deformities are
malformations on the smooth surface of
the skin
the skin skin is no longer smooth it has
these wrinkles yeah similarly space-time
the fabric of space-time the
four-dimensional space-time that itself
could have had wrinkles
that formed in the very early universe
so what would be the property of
such a wrinkle such a cosmic string
see it's like this
let's say i put my finger over here and
i travel all the way around here
and come back to the same point
i will travel a full 360 degrees yes we
know that that's what geometry teaches
us in school yeah
so you take a
pencil a finger or whatever you go all
the way around and come back to the
initial point you will traverse a full
360 degrees
let's say you have a cosmic string let's
say you encounter a cosmic string yes
and you try to go all the way around
so you go there you start at an initial
point you travel all the way around and
you reach back at the original initial
point
you will find that you have traveled
less than 360 degrees
that is a defect in the fabric of
space-time itself
yeah it's going to break all the laws of
geometry and everything
so that's what it is
it is ext these these cosmic strings are
supposed to be extremely thin
yeah
and they could go on to up to the edge
ends of the universe so almost
infinitely long if the universe is i
mean
they would extend beyond the observable
universe and as the universe expands
they also get stretched thinner and
thinner but they don't break
so
these are the topological defects that
could have formed in the very early
universe you could have had very large
amounts of numbers of cosmic strings but
as the universe expands they would
become further and further spread apart
and maybe it's very hard
to observe it now cosmic strings if they
exist they would have uh
they would be gravitationally massive
they would
work
uh
space time
so they they could create gravitational
lensing so that could be one way of
detecting them second so they would have
this gravitational effects they could
create gravitational lensing
uh
and yeah there would be these defects in
space-time so if you go around them you
would end up traversing less than 360
degrees
so that's what cosmic rings are people
have been searching for them nobody has
found them yet but yeah it doesn't mean
they don't exist it means that
if they do exist they could be so
rare and the space is so massive that it
would be very hard to detect them
now what is the relationship between
cosmic strings and wormholes no
relationship actually no relationship
but the thing about wormholes is this if
you want to construct or create a
wormhole
which is
a hole in the fabric of spacetime itself
it it's it's a it could be a
hypothetical way of allowing per people
allowing someone to travel vast
distances
through a shortcut called a wormhole so
verbal
is something that
is a solution to einstein's equations of
general relativity the thing about
verbals is that they want to snap shut
so verbals have an opening two openings
and a neck
this neck neck wants to snapshot
immediately
yeah
and the the point at which is snapshots
will be a black hole
that's how it is so it's very hard to
keep a wormhole open
to keep a wormhole open you would need
some exotic matter in the in the throat
of the wormhole something like
negative mass
which would have ripples the form of
gravity which would keep the wormholes
throat open and won't allow it to snap
shut or
you could thread a cosmic string
through a wormhole and that would
prevent the wormhole from closing so
that way you could engineer a mole that
stays open
if you know where a cosmic string is and
you can you can acquire it and you can
put thread it through a wormhole's
throat yeah
so that is one way in which you could
have a traversable wormhole but then
obviously you will have to deal with the
gravitational effects of the cosmic
string and the very strange properties
that it has of of
having these
you know less than 360 degree travel
through it all around all that yeah
so yeah that in brief is what cosmic
strings are
dash plays again wow today is dash
places day
so the question is hypothetically if we
have an indestructible container with a
hole continually getting filled with
hydrogen with more increasing pressure
that's forming inside what will happen
will hydrogen turn to helium in future
more if yes what happens to remaining
protons and neutrons all right
so what you are proposing here my dear
friend is a thought experiment a
gadanken experiment
so we don't have to
build this indestructible container and
fill it with hydrogen
and keep feeling it we can do this
experiment purely in our thoughts we
know the laws of physics so let's see
what happens
so let's say you have this this magical
container that is indestructible nothing
can destroy it and it has a fixed
diameter fixed radius yeah
you no matter how much
pressure it has inside it it won't
change the radius won't change it won't
break or whatever
so let's say you have this
indestructible container you start
filling it you start pumping in hydrogen
gas
so as more and more hydrogen molecules
get inside hydrogen atoms go inside yeah
the pressure inside the chamber
container will increase
as the pressure increases you're going
to have an increase corresponding
increase of temperature so the pressure
keeps on increasing the temperature also
keeps on increasing
and the density keeps on increasing
eventually at some point in time you
will have a density which is similar to
the density inside the sun
that's when you will have nuclear fusion
which will ignite
if you have a density similar to the
density of the sun you will also have a
temperature
similar to that of the sun and these
conditions
as you keep on pumping in more hydrogen
gas these conditions will ignite nuclear
fusion of hydrogen into helium and if
you keep on pumping more and more and
more hydrogen gas you're gonna have a
star inside
the the ignition of fusion itself is the
formation of a star yep
and if you pump in more and more
hydrogen you're gonna have more and more
fuel that gets converted into into into
helium
and eventually all the hydrogen will get
converted into helium and if you pour
more hydrogen in um eventually you could
have a proper stellar uh
cycle
you know
as the pressure keeps on increasing
the helium itself will undergo fusion
and give rise to heavier and heavier
elements and that sort of thing will go
on
so yeah that's an interesting thought
experiment that's how you can create a
star if you have this sort of container
you can create a star within it yeah
what happens to remaining protons and
neutrons well
the remaining protons and neutrons will
be part of these your newer elements
and eventually if you just keep on
pumping in hydrogen indefinitely you
will have so much density that this
whole thing becomes a black hole and
then we don't know what's inside
yeah
and if it becomes a black hole it may
eat up your industry indestructible
container too because i think black
holes can eat even that so yeah that
seems to be the end stage of this
thought experiment interesting thought
experiment
good good imagination i like it
karthik says is our universe created
from nothing
well we don't know
we had another question about what came
before the universe right so uh
we don't know what came before the
universe
was
is the universe part of a bigger
multiverse kind of thing
yeah is it so
what came before the big before the big
bang was there
an older universe before before this
universe is are we living in a cyclic
universe do we have a big crunch and a
big bounce kind of thing
a big bounce could happen because of lqg
loop quantum gravity
um
is our universe a simulation
that is also a possibility yeah
it's not impossible it's certainly
plausible
it would not break any of the laws of
physics or anything we know
so yeah we don't have the answers to
this very big question so they're very
big questions that are being asked over
here
what came before the universe what were
the ingredients from which our universe
was constructed and created we don't
know
we know that the universe at the very
beginning was just this
singularity kind of thing
infinitely small infinitely dense
infinitely hot
and the space-time and pure energy
inside yeah just pure energy
then space time expanded for whatever
reason we don't know what triggered that
off
but the expansion happened inflation
happened then you had the formation of
mass coalescence of mass out of energy
and then the whole history of the
universe but what happened before that
what was there before the universe we
don't know
we wrote the answers maybe someday we we
may have them the answers some answers
maybe we want we don't know
but yeah we we don't have the answers to
these questions but these are good
questions that drive us forward and keep
us curious
dr nishte gongay says why do the masses
struggle with math and physics any
special reason for that
yeah typically the scariest subjects in
school college etc are math and physics
math is scary because you have to solve
these difficult problems and physics is
scary because it uses math
without math you can't do physics so
these are the two scariest subjects now
so the real question is why is math so
difficult why is math so scary if math
were easy physics would not be easy
would not be difficult either
so the reason why masses struggle with
math you know math is the simplest and
easiest thing in the world
but it has to be taught properly
the reason why most people struggle with
math is because teachers
teach you something and they assume that
you have understood everything most
teachers are
mediocre teachers they don't know how to
explain things simply
the key to teaching i believe is to make
things as simple as possible
a teacher should not try to show off how
intelligent and how brilliant they are
they have to
keep things as
simple as as humanly possible and teach
it in that manner and make sure that the
recipient the student is actually
understanding what is being taught most
teachers are like repeat after me this
is this is what i write on the
blackboard you copy it down and now you
start solving problems
and they don't care whether the student
has understood what what has they've
been trying to teach i remember as a kid
myself i had this terrible teacher
i don't know what standard i was in
third standard four seven i was learning
decimals
you know decimal places and all and you
have these problems in which you are to
do additions
of numbers with decimal places and i
clearly had not understood what decimals
are because the answer which i gave had
two or three different decimal places
3.1.2.3 or something like that
you know eventually i got it right
through self-study
yeah
so that's how it is you know
these simple concepts have to be
explained clearly and properly
if you don't do it the kid the student
won't understand it and then they will
try to memorize things you don't
memorize things in mathematics you
understand things conceptually and then
more advanced concepts are built on top
of the simple concepts and if you don't
understand the simpler concepts
themselves then how are you ever going
to understand the more advanced concepts
so if you don't understand fractions you
don't understand decimals
then how are you ever going to
understand trigonometry or algebra
yeah and then how are you ever going to
understand higher concepts like things
like calculus and matrices and linear
algebra and what not
so and if you don't have the
fundamentals down clearly there is no
way you can understand higher
mathematics
and it is always because of bad
instruction poor teaching
that
the fundamentals are shaky shaky in most
people yeah
so that's why the masses struggle with
math and physics because of bad teaching
because of bad teachers
i believe anybody can master mathematics
mathematics is just pure logic it's the
simplest and easiest thing in the world
provided it is taught properly and the
foundations are built properly then you
can study then you can learn any kind of
mathematics and if you are good at math
well you gotta be good at physics it's
just a given
so the special reason
why the masses struggle with math and
physics is because most teachers 99 of
95 of teachers are very poor mediocre
and they don't care whether the students
learn or not and they are not able to
to communicate effectively and teach
effectively and they don't ensure that
they
take the feedback from the students
whether the students understood or not
and they just go on forward and forward
and that's that's why
this happens
current says how to deal with harder
topics in mathematics
to deal with harder topics in
mathematics ensure that you have
mastered the simpler topics
right
if you master the simpler topics if you
master the fundamentals the basics then
you will have no
great trouble
the topics that build on top of that
yeah
so if you want to understand
multiplication you have to first master
addition
and maybe subtraction as well
because what is multiplication it is
repeated addition
what is three times eight it is you take
three and you add it you take keep on
adding three eight times that's three
times eight
so to
master
so to understand multiplication you do
first properly master addition
then you once you do some multiplication
you do then you can go into
division and things like that and so on
so forth so
to deal with harder topics in
mathematics you have to ensure that your
fundamentals your basics are very very
clear you have mastered thoroughly then
you can move on to harder topics of
course eventually you will reach a stage
where even the best fundamentals and all
that will not be able to help you master
certain topics because eventually
mathematics becomes really abstract
and most people can't deal with that
only genius level mathematicians can
deal with certain kinds of mathematics
right ramanujans and john nash's and all
that
so uh but most people not don't need to
understand mathematics at that level
so the simplest thing is master the
basics master the fundamentals how do
you master that
problem solving solve hundreds of
problems thousands of problems
yeah that's it done
solemn vis said says
it's believed that india's very own area
is the konkala pass on the border of
on the line of actual control between
india and chinese occupied aksai chin
anyway locals on both sides of the
border believe there is an underground
ufo base in this region
please enlighten us to inspire
okay let's see where is this konkala
place let's do that
uh let's put the
map on the screen
and let's
search for it
where is it zoom in boom there you are
let's take a look at
the
terrain
so this is the region
let's zoom out a little and let's see
where it is
okay
so as you can see it's actually within
india but it's on the line of actual
control between
indian territory and chinese occupied
territory
uh so
so what's the deal with this place
so it seems that there have been reports
of unexplained aerial phenomena so what
what we call ufos yeah
there have been some picture let's see
what the pictures look like let's see
konkala
let's see what it looks like
and let's put that on the screen give me
a second let me put that on the screen
is there something interesting that the
screen is offering us
here we are aha
certain strange images have been
captured
not sure how
true this is
obviously the images are quite grainy
but yeah it is said that there is
there is uh there are phenomena over
here that uh
cannot be explained
through
conventional explanations and maybe
there are ufos there there may be a ufo
based underground ufo base who knows
what it is
locals on both sides of the border i
don't know about the other side of the
border of the lac
yeah and there have been many such
reports in the himalayan regions even
the mount kailash region people have
photographed
even taken videos of strange
unexplainable lights
near the summit of the mountain and so
on
so we don't know what it is i don't have
the information i don't have the any
idea of what's really happening i've not
been there and i'm i'm obviously not
privy to any classified or sensitive
information
how can
what are the possible explanations of
these ufos
one is that
maybe the army the air force is testing
certain
aircraft that have been that have not
been revealed support to the public you
know futuristic aircraft and spacecraft
that may have those circular designs or
whatever there is a possibility
or maybe there are actual aliens that
are visiting these places for whatever
reason or maybe it's just some defect or
artifact in the camera lens or whatever
that is causing such images so we don't
know
but as long as we don't capture
undeniable
unambiguous evidence we will not know
right
so uh
what i can tell you is that we don't
know what's happening there
in the future if if more evidence
emerges we'll know but as of now we
don't have an idea
santosh says i have heard that aliens
have infiltrated human society
and some of the prominent world leaders
are actually aliens
and they have a grand plan of turning
the human species into fodder of aliens
it reminds me of a series a science
science fiction series i watched as a
kid
it was called it was called v
wi-fi series v
ah let me show that to you
so this is the newer remake of that i
don't know how good that was but this is
the original one so in this science
fiction series
you had these uh aliens who came in
okay who come to earth on this massive
giant spaceships here that look like uh
flying saucers
and they look like humans but they are
hiding the true nature because beneath
their skin they are reptiles
you know reptilian faces and all that
and
their their objective is to enslave
humanity
and you and use humanity for food or
something like that
uh yeah so that's the kind of story it
was and it was i kind of loved it
this was i think this came out in the
1980s or something
so not
not many people remember the series but
it was very entertaining and very
exciting for me because i loved aliens
and i loved science fiction it was the
perfect intersection of two genres for
me
so yeah that's the kind of uh
that's the kind of hypothesis that we
are seeing here that aliens have
infiltrated human society and some of
the prominent world leaders are actually
aliens well some leaders i can actually
think of who do look like aliens
somewhat i will not name them for
obvious reasons but
it's an interesting prospect
um
do we have evidence for this obviously
not but yeah there are these theories
conspiracy theories about reptilians or
whatever which is what this series was
about yeah
so yeah who knows
maybe
some some world leaders actually do look
like
they kind of do remind you of aliens
anyway
okay with that we have come to the end
of today's questions but let's take a
look at some um
live questions you guys got some
questions for me oh i can see some
interesting names coming up
mark who's mark i wonder who's mark
[Laughter]
okay let's take some live live chat
questions
i can see some names from india also
turning up
as candidate alien leaders
okay saurabh says what is a warp drive
and warp speed
so this is uh
what is a warp drive it is
the basic
idea is the warping of space time
so like we have discussed many times
we live in four dimensional space time
that's what
general relativity tells us it is an
extremely successful theory that
explains everything we see at the large
scale structure of the universe and all
that so what general relativity tells us
that we live in four dimensional space
time that's the fabric of the space time
that we are immersed in
now we know that gravity according to
general relativity warps bends space
time
so what is a warp drive it's a
hypothetical theoretical drive
in which you can use the whopping of
space time to create a bubble that
travels within space-time or something
like that and it can possibly travel
faster than the speed of light
so you're not actually breaking the laws
of physics
you're creating a bubble that travels
within space-time the warping of
space-time the ripples in space-time so
to say travel faster than light which is
allowed
yeah that sort of thing
so that is what a warp drive is it is
what you find in science fiction uh
novels and movies and series uh
warp drive was popularized by star trek
i believe yes warp drive bob speed all
that so warp speed is a warp drive in
operation which
achieves super luminal velocities but
yeah well
um
obviously we don't have the technology
to do that maybe someday in the future
we could have it it could be allowed by
the laws of
general relativity
yeah
okay
what are the questions
utkar says how energetic particles like
photons could be something but have no
mass
so
photons
why don't they have mass
because they do not interact with the
higgs field
in quantum field theory the world is
made up of fields everything we see is
just an illusion
all particles are local
um
they are local
disturbances in space-time in in these
these fields so there is an
electron field and every electron in my
body is is part of that electron field
and so on so there are 17 fields in the
standard model
and there is the higgs field
so photons
photons
are particles or bosons that do not
interact with the eggs field the higgs
field is what gives the universe its
mass
the interaction with various particles
with the higgs field gives these
particles mass if a particle interacts
strongly with the eggs field it has a
high mass if a particle interacts very
weakly with the higgs field it has a low
mass and if a particle simply doesn't
interact with the higgs field it has no
mass
so photons do not interact with the
higgs field therefore they have no mass
but they have energy
photons are packets of energy yes
now
we have the very famous the most famous
equation in physics e equals m3 squared
by which energy has an equivalent mass
and mass of any current energy and so
that that's how photons do
have energy which is equivalent to mass
and that's why you can construct a black
hole out of photons only
you know you can construct a black hole
mathematically using the laws of quantum
mechanics
and you can create a black hole just out
of photons
it's a different kind of black hole from
the black hole of general relativity but
yeah it does you can actually you
actually actually can do that
so yeah that's your answer dear sir
let's see what else do we have
current says what will happen when
fossil fuels get exhausted well then
all of that will be released as carbon
into the atmosphere you'll have a
significant amount of carbon
uh in the atmosphere a lot of global
warming and all that yeah the the global
warming will be con
will happen because of that and of
course we will have no more fossil fuels
no more petrol diesel
kerosene jet fuel whatever to burn no
more coal and then we will have to look
for other sources of of energy
so we better get going and start
start you know experimenting with
various different technologies
so yeah that's
at the rate at which we're going we
could have maybe a century more of
fossil fuels and then everything would
possibly
uh
get exhausted and then we'll have to
find some other other ways of
of of
acquiring or extracting energy
um people are asking questions about
history i don't know why they do that on
a science day please don't do that
we'll discuss history tomorrow i promise
today it is about
science all right where are we what do
we have the um
[Music]
what's my opinion on home of homeopathy
homeopathy is the placebo effect it's
so homeopathic practitioners have found
excellent ways of inducing the placebo
effect and that's why it seems to work
in certain cases yeah but
it obviously can't cure cancer or any
serious diseases
so that's my opinion it's it's
it's a nice way of inducing the placebo
effect
um
what is quantum entanglement it's it's
when
you have a system of two or more
particles that has a single wave
function so you can't describe the the
the
any of the particles alone you have to
describe the system as a whole and if
you know the properties of one part of
the system you immediately know the
properties instantaneously of the other
part of the system let's say you have
a particle with spin zero which splits
into two particles with one particle
with spin up with particle with spin
down and they go in different directions
after a million million years they are
let's say 10 light years away from each
other so the distance is 10 light years
now let's say i i measure one of the
particles and i see it is spin up then i
will immediately instantaneously know
that the other particle which is 10
light years away has been down
so i know
by looking at one particle
instantaneously the properties of the
other particle which is 10 light years
away or maybe a million light years away
so you kind of have this information
that i'm getting about about a particle
that is 100 that is a million light
years away instantaneously so that looks
like information traveling faster than
the speed of light kind of right
but it's not quite so but yeah that's
how it is it's a very spooky property
and that's what quantum integral
entanglement is
in very brief in very
yeah
um
what else do we have
pratik says can spinning black holes
radiate gravitational waves as
accelerating masses do radiate yes
spinning black holes will give
what they will do is
they will kind of drag space-time
with the spin so the black hole is
spinning and the spinning of the black
hole
will cause space time to be dragged
along kind of with it
so let's say you have a ball in water
and you spin it the water kind of drags
around is dragged along with the with
the spinning of the ball it creates this
vortex kind of shape right so similarly
a spinning black hole will drag space
time with it and any kind of
uh
any any such thing in space time will
give off gravitational waves
so yes spinning black holes do radiate
gravitational waves
merging black holes radiate
gravitational waves and so on yeah so
that's the answer they do radiate
gravitational waves
does life exist on other galaxies well
we don't know
we don't know it may be so but we have
never found any unambiguous evidence of
that
um
what is a white hole a white hole is a
certain kind of solution of the einstein
equations of general relativity in which
which is the opposite of a black hole
so white holes so we know that black
holes are in the event horizon white
holes also have an event horizon
for the black hole for a black hole the
event horizon is a point of no return if
you're falling towards a black hole if
you cross the event horizon you can
never come back out in the case of a
white hole
the even horizon is the place beyond
which you cannot go inside a white hole
is like a time reversed black hole a
white hole spews out matter and energy
and radiation it cannot absorb anything
it's like a time reversed black hole
and apart from that a white hole could
have very similar properties to a black
hole the gravitational effects would be
more or less the same
so in some cases in in some galaxies you
have these
active galactic nuclei
which spew of enormous amounts of
light and radiation and mass you know
these jets of radiation coming out of
them
some people believe some scientists
believe they actually could be white
holes spewing after it or spraying out
radiation and matter
and we still don't know how to figure
out whether it's a black hole or a white
hole so yeah so that's what a white hole
is it is like a time reversed black hole
um
do you believe in the multiverse we
don't know if if a multiverse exists
because we have no evidence of it but it
is possible it could exist so i say 50
50 maybe yes maybe no i don't know i
don't believe things
there's no belief in science you look at
the
the evidence and the data you have and
then you based your
understanding of the universe based on
that on the evidence do we have evidence
of a multiverse no
so that would integrate indicate that a
multiverse
well that doesn't prove that the
multiverse doesn't exist so that's why
it's not exactly science it's not
falsifiable so it's possible but we
don't know
gaurav says what do you think about the
theory of brain capacity use that what
if we use only 15 or 20 of the brain
um
that's not quite true
they there are these popular science
fiction depictions of humans only use
two percent of the brain or ten percent
of the brain capacity that is not very
quite quite quite true
um
what are the movie uh limitless or
something right limitless you take a
brain and suddenly you expand and you
use all of your brain capacity
the brain functions in a certain way
you start fiddling with it you're gonna
have problems um
so i do not agree
with the theory of brain capacity that
only five percent or ten percent is
being used there is something called the
subconscious brain that we are not aware
of the subconscious mind that is active
but we are not aware of it
you know
and
it manifests itself in a variety of ways
when we are asleep we are dreaming
that is the subconscious mind at work
when you play sports and you have
learned behaviors that is subconscious
mind coming and manifesting itself in
your in your
let's say you're you're cricket bowling
or golf swing or whatever that's your
learned
something that you that is a result of
your muscle memory
and so on so it's not quite true that we
use only a little bit of the brains per
capacity we actually use all of it
okay where else are we what else do we
have
um
lucy uh yeah a movie called lucy i think
i'd seen it
uh what else
so this is a question i asked a few
seconds ago is can there possibly be
intelligent life on other planets of the
solar system before on earth possible
but we don't have evidence possible
it's not impossible
okay what else
[Applause]
my opinion on sheldon cooper from big
bang theory it was a fun series to watch
initially i had actually watched a few
episodes of the first season it was very
funny very hilarious physicists aren't
quite like that you know today i think
everyone believed that physicists behave
like sheldon cooper
not quite the case but yeah it was it
was
a very very very funny series
especially in the first season
afterwards i don't know what happens and
sheldon sheldon cooper was obviously the
most interesting and most
the funniest character yeah the
stereotypical archetypal
theoretical physicist
do we have any other interesting
questions
shaheen
says what's a magnetar
i think
a magnetar is a highly magnetized pulsar
if i'm not mistaken a pulsar is a star
that
that pulses pulses in radio frequency
yeah
so a few times every second or every few
seconds it gives off this radio radio
frequency pulses
uh radio waves
uh and initially it was when pulsars
were discovered it was believed that it
was thought these are signals of from
alien civilizations because they were so
repetitive and so
i mean
yeah it's so well
exactly spaced apart in time yeah but
eventually it was discovered that it's a
kind of extra physical object a pulsar
i think a magneto is a is a highly
magnetized pulsar if i'm not mistaken
uh i haven't studied magnetos in depth
but yeah i think that's what it is
how can we use wikipedia intelligently
so for science when it comes to science
wikipedia is a good source reasonably
good source the thing about wikipedia is
that it's it can be edited essentially
by anybody so you have to be careful
about the information if you want to
study science you better study science
from your textbooks or from uh
textbooks are the best source yeah but
yeah wikipedia is good it is good for
referring to things and looking at the
related research so i would say the most
intelligent way of using wikipedia is to
look at the sources the references that
wikipedia gives yeah and you can look at
the references because they could be
more authoritative but you always have
to remember at the end of the day that
wikipedia is
could be wrong about various things when
it comes to history it's very often
wrong
there's a lot of distortion when it
comes to history but in science it's
more typically a better resource than
for history
so the best way the most intelligent way
to use wikipedia is to use it for
gathering good references but then you
will have to study the references and
judge for yourself whether they are
reliable or not but it's a great place
to
gather references
okay let's take one more question for
today once again you get questions about
history
her says don't donate to wikipedia
that's the best way to intelligently use
wikipedia i agree with her
don't donate to wikipedia
um
anything else anything else once again
i'm getting questions about history
i
you know there's a reason why i stopped
doing those video chats
you know remember i used to do video
chats once in a while i would invite
people to talk to me face to face on
video chat
i stopped doing that the primary reason
is that people simply don't follow the
rules
if today is a science session and i get
somebody on video chat and they start
asking me a question about history
now i feel sorry to say to tell them to
go away
and you're breaking the rules because
as i said
people simply will not follow
instructions for some reason
today is
today's live stream is about science but
i see over here in the live chat people
asking me questions again and again and
again about history
i just don't get it why why do you guys
do this
stick to science for today tomorrow you
can ask questions about history tomorrow
while i am saying this people ask me
this
okay this is actually
it's not about history how do you return
so much knowledge okay that's not a bad
question okay
uh how do i retain so much knowledge
how do i write knowledge first of all i
read a lot
i've been reading a lot since i was a
kid
maybe since
the first novel full length novel i read
i read it when i was seven years old
it was a novel written in the 19th
century called the coral island
so yeah i've been reading for a very
long time since i was a kid and my
reading speed is very very high i can
read very fast
i can read a single page in like a
matter of seconds it's something that i
have developed over a long period of
time so yeah it's not some superpower
that i have it's it's like a muscle you
build a muscle over time it takes years
to build muscles right similarly the
reading speed becomes better as you read
more and more so my reduced reading
speed is very high i am very comfortable
reading a lot it's what i've been doing
for years so typically at least for me i
i find it easier to gather knowledge by
reading than by watching videos
for some people podcasts are a great
thing fine
everybody is different so for some
people can gain a lot of knowledge by
watching podcasts by listening to
podcasts by watching various youtube
videos for me the best way to gain
knowledge from my perspective is by
reading secondly
i always give myself permission to
forget what i read
i i tell myself i will remember only
what i find interesting so i buy books i
many books i don't finish them
or in some books i only read certain
sections whatever i find interesting and
the moment it stops
i mean i it stops
interestingly
i give up
i try to try to read a little bit more
but if it stops holding my interest i
give up you know i stop i stop reading
so i give myself the permission to
forget everything
that way
i remem remember what i find interesting
and that's how i learn
so typically if you have a textbook and
you are told to study it you you are
told to memorize every goddamn thing you
have to memorize every sentence you
remember every equation you have to
remember every line or whatever it is
that's not how i read that's not my
study i give myself permission to forget
as much as i can as much as possible my
objective is to forget everything only
written what is interesting
and that's how i've always operated and
that's how i learn
so maybe it's something you guys can try
if
if you think it makes sense to you
and with that we are at the end of
today's session we have once again
crossed two hours which is the objective
these days
right all right so today's session is
done thank you very much for the
questions and for the
wonderful chat
and i will see you in tomorrow's session
which will be a different topic history
uh history
geopolitics current office etc
until then take care
and
i'll see you soon
bye